<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Xcode | dispatch_async]]></title>
  <link href="http://mgreiner.github.io/blog/categories/xcode/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mgreiner.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-19T08:13:11-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mgreiner.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mike Greiner]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Breakpoint Actions in Xcode 5.1]]></title>
    <link href="http://mgreiner.github.io/blog/2014/02/12/breakpoint-actions-in-xcode-5-dot-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-12T08:40:34-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mgreiner.github.io/blog/2014/02/12/breakpoint-actions-in-xcode-5-dot-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I got a nice suprise the first time I fired up the debugger in Xcode 5.1. Expressions in breakpoint actions now work the way I’ve always wanted them to.</p>

<p>Breakpoint actions were introduced in Xcode back in <em>X</em>. They allow developers to define the actions that are taken each time a breakpoint is hit in the debugger. Supported actions include logging a message to the console, playing a sound, running an AppleScript or shell script, capturing an OpenGS EL frame or executing an LLDB command.</p>

<p>One of the most useful breakpoint actions is the ability to log messages to the console. This kind of <a href="&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tracing_(software)&quot;">software tracing</a> is probably the most common kind of debugging on any platform anywhere.</p>

<p>How many times have you written code that looks like this?</p>

<div><table class="CodeRay"><tr>
  <td class="line-numbers"><pre><a href="#n1" name="n1">1</a>
<a href="#n2" name="n2">2</a>
<a href="#n3" name="n3">3</a>
<a href="#n4" name="n4">4</a>
<a href="#n5" name="n5">5</a>
</pre></td>
  <td class="code"><pre>- (<span class="directive">void</span>)setFoo:(NSString *)foo
{
    NSLog(<span class="error">@</span><span class="string"><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span><span class="content">Setting foo to: %@</span><span class="delimiter">&quot;</span></span>, foo);
    _foo = [foo copy];
}
</pre></td>
</tr></table>
</div>

<p>This works very well for keeping track of what <code>foo</code> is being set to – except that:</p>

<ul>
  <li>If <code>foo</code> is set often in your code, this adds a lot of noise in the console or your log file</li>
  <li>If you want to change what you’re logging, you need to recompile the code</li>
  <li>You can’t do this for apps or libraries that you don’t have the source code for.</li>
</ul>

<p>If instead you use a break point action like this:</p>

<p><img class="left" src="images/example-breakpoint-action.png" title="‘A Breakpoint Action in Xcode 5.1’ ‘An example of a breakpoint action in Xcode 5.1’" ></p>

<p>You can log the same value without inserting a <code>NSLog</code> statement in your code. The <code>@</code> delimeters indicate to the debugger that it should evaluate the delimited text as an LLDB expression. However in prior versions of Xcode this did not work very well with Objective-C objects. The above example would yied something like this in the debugger console:</p>

<pre><code>Setting foo to: 0x0000000100003c18
</code></pre>

<p>The LLDB expression command used with an object here is displaying the object’s memory address – which is rarely what I want. Ideally, I’d see the equivalent of <code>expr -o foo</code> (or the shorter gdb throw-back <code>po foo</code>) which invokes the <code>-debugDescription</code> method of my object.</p>

<p>My workaround for this was usually to add two breakpoint actions, a Log Message action and a Debugger Command action:</p>

<p><img class="left" src="http://url/of/image" title="‘Two Breakpoint Actions to Log a Value’ “Using two breakpoint actions to log a variable’s value”" ></p>

<p>This has the obvious disadvantage that it’s more work and two lines of output are produced instead of one. But in Xcode 5.1, the debugger now shows the summary of the object instead of its address. So now when I create the same breakpoint action in Xcode 5.1, I see this:</p>

<pre><code>Setting foo to: @"bar"
</code></pre>

<p>This not the <code>-debugDescription</code> of the object, it’s the summary that you would see in variables view of the debug area. For strings you’ll see the contents of the string. For collections, you’ll see the number of objects contained in the collection (to see the contents of the collection, just use @[collection debugDescription]@ as your expression).</p>

<p>If you set the breakpoint to <em>Automatically continue after evaluating</em> then you effectively have a tracing mechanism that requires neither recompiling or even having the source code.</p>

<p>You can also set the debugger’s console to display only <em>Debugger Output</em>. to show only the output from your breakpoint actions. This will allow you to easily focus on what you’re tracing and ignore the rest of the logging noise.</p>

<p><img class="left http://url/of/image ‘The Xcode console windoe set to <em>Debugger" src="Output</em>’"></p>

<p>Using several breakpoints in this way with conditions applied and enabling/disabling them when necessary becomes a very powerful and flexible debugging mechanism.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
